India is now being forced to ration
diesel fuel for the first time maybe
ever. At the same time, global stocks of
crude oil have fallen to their lowest
since 2003. Even here in the US,
inventories have been drained to levels
we haven't witnessed in over 20 years.
In other words, as hopes for a peace
deal with Iran rise, we now have to turn
our attention to that next critical
stage because as potential for conflict
fades,
this thing still isn't over. With oil
flow historically restricted over the
last 3 months, there are consequences
which are just now starting to be felt.
We have little idea how much damage has
been done and how much of it might be
permanent. It's also going to take quite
some time to get production moving again
and then be able to replace the massive
amount of oil that came out of
inventories including in places like
China. What the Chinese have done over
the last 3 months has been utterly
extraordinary and how they respond over
the next couple weeks will be absolutely
critical to the path that oil prices
take from here. That's what we need to
watch carefully. There's going to be
some selling euphoria especially once
the shorts go piling in but after that
initial downward bounce, that's what we
need to see. How the market prices this
coming next stage of the energy shock
which is hopefully the cleanup phase.
We're already getting market signals
this past week about what that could
possibly look like. So, we'll take a
look into the curve, the inventories and
like India, just how far off of normal
the world has gotten to be.
So, Steve, we've got some what looks to
be good news. At least the market, the
oil market anyway, is taking it as okay,
this may be closer to the end than not
but the rest of the oil market is
saying, well, we've come this far. We've
been able to get this far through a
couple of different couple of different
means and measures but those the clock
is still ticking on those.
>> Yeah, absolutely Jeff because, you know,
it's almost like the real shock is yet
to come. So, you have the earthquake and
then you have the aftershock and
sometimes the aftershock is far worse.
And I think the perception is for a lot
of people it's like it's like a spigot,
a water spigot. You just go out into
your yard and well, you you turned it
down because, you know, we did had too
much, you know, we didn't have anywhere
to put all this oil. We'll just turn it
right back up, but that's not the case
at all. Just to keep the infrastructure
running, assuming there's no other
damage to it, you've got to run a
minimum amount through. Some wells, they
need to produce a minimum amount of oil
barrels every day or else things go
wrong. So, the issue I think everyone
doesn't realize and this is I think the
big shoe to drop over the next couple
months is the fact that supply in some
cases could come on within a week, but
there could be supply that takes months,
years, and maybe even never. And the
problem is even though we're seeing the
reaction in the market today saying,
"Hey, it looks like oil prices are going
to come down." The problem is what
happens as we look around the world and
we see that inventories are depleted, we
see all the supply chain that is damaged
or needs repair or needs anything. Next
thing you know, the odds of oil prices
going back up. And then you think about
at the worst possible time, that
probability is going up.
>> Yeah, so the risk here, Steve, right, is
the old adage up like a rocket, down
like a feather, right? You know, oil
prices scream higher when the supply
gets restricted and then
it's kind of sticky on the way back
down. That's certainly the case with
gasoline. It takes a little while for
lower oil prices to filter through the
system. So, the danger is if we have,
you know, like I said, the clock is
ticking. We have to work work our way
through what has already been physical
shortfalls around the play. Again, India
is a big one. India has, you know, close
to the Middle East, big buyer of Middle
Eastern oil. One of the most directly
affected by this the closure of the
Strait of Hormuz Hormuz and lack of
production and lack of flow of petroleum
through the world to the point now where
India has okay. They are now restricting
get diesel the rationing diesel fuel,
which is a big deal for India. Let me
read what happened what Bloomberg wrote
on Friday.
The government announced rare
restrictions on diesel sales capping
purchases at 200 L per day per customer.
Um Friday's move to curb diesel sales
means purchases will be capped at 200 L
per day per customer. State-owned
retailers struggled to cope with
increased demand as they sold fuel below
market rates. That's central planning
for you. With some reporting pumps going
dry across the country. I don't recall
such a drastic step being taken in the
past, according to Prashant Vashisht,
senior vice president ratings agency
ICRA. Other countries have already done
it, but it is rare for India. If you
have a retirement account, and if you've
ever wondered whether crypto belongs
inside of it, BlockFi Trust IRA is
something worth looking into. Now, most
crypto IRA platforms are self-directed.
They give you access, but you have to
decide what to buy, when to sell, when
to rebalance. BlockFi Trust IRA is
different. It's designed as a managed
crypto IRA solution, meaning there's a
portfolio strategy behind the account.
Custody is provided through SFOX, and
the strategy includes active portfolio
management and rebalancing inside the
IRA. Now, BlockFi Trust IRA states that
its portfolio system has outperformed
Bitcoin buy and hold by over 250
percentage points since 2020. Now, past
performance does not guarantee future
results, and crypto investments can
indeed lose value, including principal.
Now, right now, eligible viewers can get
up to a $2,500 crypto bonus when they
open and fund an account. Terms,
conditions, funding minimums, and
eligibility requirements apply. To learn
more, go to youradollar crypto.com.
Now, this is a paid advertisement, not
financial, investment, tax, or
retirement advice. Crypto is volatile
and may lose value, and past performance
is no guarantee of future results. Plus,
terms do apply. So, again, the clock is
ticking because we need to get oil
restored, not just to get it restored
back to where it was. We got to start
filling some of these places that have
run dry. So, if India is rationing
diesel fuel, it's going to be some time
before, you know, feedstock petroleum
shows up in India. Therefore, it has to
go through the refining process and the
shipping process, gets logistic, you
know, logistical issues, to transport
it. India could be without sufficient
diesel for several weeks, if not months,
further on. So, that's really the
question we have to grapple with. Okay,
now we know maybe the conflict is over,
maybe we're on the good side where
production's coming back, but how long
is that, you know, how steep is that
curve back to normalization? That's
where we need to look from this point
forward.
>> And you know, Jeff, that's a great point
because you know, you look at
inventories, as you said, they've been
depleted. So, you know, the consumer's
going to be thinking, "Okay, the war's
over, gas prices are going to come down.
Perfect, summer's hitting, maybe I can
go do something." But they don't realize
that these oil producers and all these
storage places, they're going to think,
"Hey, we have an opportunity to bring
them up to, you know, we'll call it
operational levels from these, you know,
absolutely minimum depleted levels." So,
their their motivation isn't going to be
to, "Hey, let's let's run a bunch of
gasoline through the refinery so we can
get you know, consumer prices down."
They're going to be thinking of, "What
if there's another shock? What if this
war isn't really over? What if something
else pops up? We have to get our
inventory levels up." And you think
about it, it's kind of like the central
bankers, "We need to raise rates so we
can lower them again." You know, it's
the same notion with these oil
producers, they're going to be thinking
the exact same logic. So, for consumers
as we head into, you know, the summer
season, is this going to mean higher
prices? And then, you know, you talk
about India, you know, lack of diesel,
you think about this at the producer
level, what this means for producer
prices, also likely to go higher. So,
the idea that, you know, perhaps that
inflation is going to just come right
down isn't so likely, at least in the
short-term future. Yeah.
>> Yeah, what we've seen in the US, let's
start there, specifically the US, the
inventories, according to the Energy
Information Administration, gasoline
inventories have tumbled. Tumbled for a
couple of reasons. One, you know,
there's there's usual drawdowns at this
time of year, but also because we've
exported a lot of gasoline, a lot of
oil. The US has tried to make up a whole
lot of that uh at least a a big chunk of
what was missing from the Iran conflict.
And so, a lot of oil went overseas. A
lot of gasoline and other products did,
too. And so, US gasoline inventories
have been drawn way, way down, and US
product inventories to a certain extent,
as well. I mean, the product
inventories, according to EIA, are as
low as they've been since 2003,
2004, 2003, depending on which source
you're talking about. But, like Steve
said, that what that means is uh the
energy system, refiners, they're going
to run the refineries hot. There's going
to be additional demand to make up those
lost inventories on top of regular
demand, assuming the regular demand
didn't fall off, which we're also
getting indications that has taken
place. But, there's going to be
additional demand to refill those those
drawn-down stocks, which is, you know,
one reason why prices shoot up, but then
they take their time coming down because
there is an adjustment period here. And
like I said before, what we now have to
figure out is, okay, how long is it
going to take to refill all these
stocks? What are the rates that we can
get? I mean, how much additional demand
is that going to create? How much How
fast is supply going to come back onto
the marketplace? Will we still need the
US and Venezuela and Brazil and some of
the marginal producers to continue to
produce excess oil because, you know,
the Middle Eastern uh facilities are
damaged, and maybe it's going to take a
lot longer. There are a number of
questions, and as we're sorting out
those questions, oil prices are not
going to go back down to $50. Where
they're eventually going to go, that's
absolutely the case. The question is,
how long they take to get there? And
that's where you look at something like
the WTI futures curve. The WTI futures
curve has flattened dramatically. And we
talked about this before, it was very
steep in back In fact, it was record
steep in backwardation as there was so
much panic buying at the front end of
the curve for immediate delivery. But,
over the last couple of weeks, as front
end prices have come back down, there
have I don't want to say resistance, but
there has been less of a a downturn in
in prices uh for contracts further out,
you know, later this year into next year
because the market is thinking, okay,
great that we have We're not going to
have the same level of panic buying at
the front, but we still don't really
have a good idea of how long it's going
to take to get everything back to
normal." And that's where we are really
focused on now is how long it takes for
oil prices to get back where they should
be, not just come down from the highs.
>> Yeah, Jeff, and that's why kind of like
I think in the short run, like as the
curve suggests, prices are going to come
down, but the question that is what
happens after that. The expectation's
going to be, "Well, they're going to
come down even more." But as we said,
it's not just the producers that are
going to be looking to refill up their
stock. What about governments and the
strategic petroleum reserves? You know,
nobody's going to want to sit around for
a while and be like, "Hey, you know
what? Everybody knows we just drew down
all of our inventories to nothing, which
means if something happens, our
military's are not going to have the
fuel and oil it needs to power itself."
That's not going to happen. Governments
are also going to be looking and saying,
"Look, we need to refill our reserves,
and we're going to do it at any cost."
Producers are going to do it. So the
likely path then is well, could see a
drop, and then all of a sudden, what we
could see is another big rally here, and
then it that's where the real squeeze
That's where that aftershock's going to
kick in because the relief that
everybody's been waiting for isn't going
to happen because the conflict went on
for so long, and inventories were
depleted to exceptionally low levels.
>> There is a world of information in all
of these curves and market signals,
including the WTI futures curve. That's
how we're going to talk about what these
curves are telling us, what these
signals are giving us, what this
information really amounts to at our
next webinar this coming June 28th. It's
a Sunday, 5:30 p.m. Eastern Time.
There's a link in the description to
sign up. We are going to go over how all
this information, the curves, the
shapes, the reshape, how to decipher it.
We've got a wealth of information at our
fingertips, and hardly anyone knows it's
there. And of those people who do, they
don't really know how to use it,
especially in something like the context
of portfolio management. So with all of
these major questions hanging over the
marketplace as well as the economy,
we're going to take a deeper look at all
of the signals that we're getting and
how to filter them into a rational
portfolio management strategy. So, I
hope you can join me Sunday, June 28th,
5:30 p.m. Eastern time. It's going to be
worth your time to attend.
>> Yeah, that's it, right, Steve? The
bounce. So, you have a lot of people who
are okay, the Trump administration, even
Iran is signaling, "Okay, they may be
very close to a deal." which is
tremendously positive news. So,
everybody's piling into the oil market.
Everybody is shorting oil because they
know the fundamental value is what we
saw in December, not what we had, you
know, in the middle of April. You know,
December oil prices were in the 50s and
heading lower. That's where oil's going
to eventually go. So, now everybody in
the marketplace is shorting the crap out
of oil. But, there's always going to be
that next step after the initial
euphoria, after the initial, you know,
shorting takes place. And I talked about
this in a video not long ago. We expect
oil prices at the front to come down and
then bounce. And the reason they're
going to bounce is the market is going
to say, "Okay, we we've gotten past all
that. The market has digested the
possibility, maybe even the good possi-
good probability that Iran's done. The
issue's over. Things are going to start
normalizing." However, as we assess the
situation, we get more data and clarity
on it, it may we may what we may find is
not what we want to find. We may find
that there are more um supply
restrictions, production costs,
production hits, all that stuff. May-
There might be a lot more there. Or,
just like you said, Steve, uh
governments are going to want to start
buying a lot more oil to refill their
strategic reserves, which is going to
keep demand elevated more than it
normally would have. China is a perfect
example. I don't think people realize
just how much the Chinese how much of a
role they played in keeping oil prices
tame over the last couple months.
Chinese imports of petroleum absolutely
crashed. You look at the numbers that
were put out by the General
Administration of Customs, physical
crude imports, not the dollar value, but
physical crude imports were down by 3%
in March, 20% in April, and 29%
in May. Now, the reason that they could
import less oil is, as Steve was just
saying, the Chinese government allowed
certain companies and certain entities
to tap their strategic petroleum
reserves. We don't know how much that's
taken place cuz the Chinese don't really
like to report their strategic assets,
but it's likely that it was pretty
substantial when you look at those
import figures. So, the Chinese are
going to want to start buying some oil
again to refill the reserves, which is
going to at the very least complicate
this next stage, complicate the pathway
from oil where it is today to back down
to 50 $50 per barrel, which means
gasoline prices, distillate prices,
diesel prices are going to be high.
This is a This is a more complicated
process than, "Okay, Iran's done, oil
goes down back to where it was."
>> Yeah, Jeff, and I think, you know, okay,
so the question then becomes is, well,
how do we get to $50 a barrel if you
guys are saying, "Look, there's going to
be a likely rebound here." Well, you
know, it kind of makes perfect sense as
you start to see this prolonged crisis.
So, you know, we know four of the last
five recessions clearly due to energy
shocks. The problem with this one is,
inventory levels again depleted so low
that everybody's going to want to stock
up. I mean, this would be like opening
your pantry and seeing no food, and
finally you're like, "Hey, there's some
food in the store." You're going to go
and buy, and then you're going to hoard
it. I mean, it's just a natural
expectation. Even if you know there's
going to be more truck loads in the week
to come, you're still going to stock up
in case something goes wrong. So, now
the risk is we could have this stretch
out not just for a few weeks. This thing
could go on for months in some places,
as you said. They could be, you know,
high energy prices for maybe a year plus
in some parts of the world just until
things normalize. And you know, we've
heard this through, you know, from a lot
of Gulf producers say, "Look, there's
damage here. There's real damage." And
some of this we can fix pretty quick. A
lot of this, yeah, it it it doesn't get
magically repaired. It takes a very long
time. And so, this is something that
consumers and the economy are going to
have to deal with as we now face
potentially what I'm thinking is going
to look like the fifth out of six last
energy shock is going to look like a
recession and that's how you get to $50
a barrel. It's not because there's such
a sudden flood of supply in the market,
it's the demand destruction, the coming
recession where everyone says, "Hey, I
don't need oil anymore because I don't
my factory doesn't need to run because
nobody's buying anything, consumers
aren't traveling, they're not driving,
businesses are laying off." That's how
you get down the next level.
>> Yeah, it's either supply restoration or
demand destruction and it could be some
of both really, but you get you get one
or the other or both of them together,
that's how oil prices get back here.
You're absolutely right, Steve, but
we've already seen the demand
destruction and the other part of the
Chinese import, yes, some companies were
tapping the strategic reserves to make
up for that inflow shortfall, but the
other part of that was demand
destruction inside of China. So, I hate
to say but the Chinese economy falling
off did the world a tremendous favor by
keeping oil prices low, but it's not for
the reasons that we would like it to be.
So, Chinese demand absolutely down
according to Reuters, Sinopec said that
which is China's largest fuel company
that gasoline sales were down 8%
year-over-year in April, which is I
think is the latest figures that we have
and diesel sales were down 6%.
Some other people estimate that gasoline
consumption may have fallen by as much
as 20% inside of China. Now, some of
that is just the accelerating economic
weakness we've been talking about. We
got a hint of that in the latest banking
data, which was again ugly. So, the
Chinese economy is in trouble to begin
with, but you get you know, potentially
a price action plus the restrictions
that the Chinese government imposed on
various parts of the economy. So, you've
got demand destruction already took
place in China. Gasoline demand in the
United States has also been
some called it tepid. That's probably
putting it most charitably, most kindly.
It's more like softening, hasn't
crashed, hasn't fallen off, but has
definitely come down, which has
cushioned the drop in gasoline
inventories to an extent, but as long
the longer gasoline prices remain above,
you know, four, four 20, four 30, four
50 per gallon in some places, and closer
to five in some of the more expensive
places, the more that US gasoline
demand's going to go down. So, yeah,
Steve, that's exactly the the the next
part of this. So, you have demand for
fuel that's going to be
that's going to be higher as some
governments start to refill their
inventories and some private sources,
right, to start to refill their their
gasoline and distillate stocks. India
needs to buy a whole ton of stuff just
to get them back into, you know, normal
functioning where they don't have to
wrestle ration diesel prices or diesel
fuel anymore. As all that takes place,
prices, they don't come down right away,
which means the chances, or not just the
chances, but the level of demand
destruction across the rest of the
economy goes up. So,
we have to be careful about when oil
prices are retracing in this next stage,
which way they go and why they're going
in which way that which direction they
might end up going.
>> And you know, Jeff, there's another
factor, because we're just assuming the
war is over and the supply's going to be
coming back online and we're going to
follow what we believe is kind of a
normal pattern of refilling inventories,
consumer demand, but there's another
factor. As you and I both live in
Florida, there's this thing called
hurricane season that tends to show up
every once in a while, and I believe it
rolls through a place called the Gulf of
America, and the problem is if we have a
bad hurricane season and we are forced
to have, you know, supply taken offline
or that there's damage done, it's going
to be even worse, because now the sudden
you're at a point where you have no
inventory, and the one place you really
do want to be producing forcibly
shutting down, it's going to make this
worse, drive prices likely right back
up, and the problem is they're likely to
stay up. And you think about the timing
of this, you know, mid-late summer
season, it's just the worst possible
time for consumers, and businesses,
well, they've already been dealing with
they they already know the reality is
they can't pass these on to consumers.
The problem is consumers already tapped
out facing potentially even more shocks
in the months to come.
>> Yeah, that's a good point about the
inventory. The inventory issue is that
it raises the level of uncertainty over
potentially any other kinds of
disruption. Let's face it, there's
there's potential all over the place
right now.
Um hurricane season is definitely a big
one. We've seen that before. With
inventories just not there, um you could
see
more volatility in oil prices than would
normally be around these types of
events. So, yeah, this is I Yeah, again,
the the main point here is that we've
seen the clock running down in a lot of
different places. India is a big one
where, you know, they're already
rationing diesel fuel. They've already
seen that type that that type of
behavior take place across across the
rest of the Asian region as well. And
then there's the other side of this,
too, which is not not just macroeconomic
consequences, but the dollar shock.
We've seen a lot of Asian governments do
get really desperate trying to either
restrict dollar flows or to try to get
them to come back to their India is
another one.
Keep coming back to India because they
have one of the biggest oil problems
that there is. You know, India has been
pulling out all the stops to try to
invite I mean, they got banks over there
paying ultra premiums on dollar
deposits, short-term dollar deposits,
too, trying to get dollars to come back
into India. So, the longer the energy
shock goes on in this next stage,
because there is a next stage, there's
actually next couple stages after the
initial conflict, the next couple stages
of the of the oil shock are in many ways
more important than the initial one. How
we resolve it and whether or not we can
resolve it quickly will make a huge
difference in how what the what the
overall consequences in the marketplace
and the economy really end up being.
>> And you know, Jeff, that's a key point
because how is this resolved? If it's
resolved with demand destruction, then
we're at the fifth of recession out of
the last six energy shocks. If there's
some other possible outcome, and I I
will just say I'm not convinced that
that's likely to happen cuz I think
we're past the point of no return, but
we would need to see so much supply
coming back online. We need to see all
the refiners running, and we would need
to see demand soften a bit just to allow
refilling these inventories. If that
could happen, we could potentially
escape this, but I just don't think
we're there. The problem but I think the
risks are bigger that we're going to see
more demand destruction. We're going to
see that this, you know, be prolonged
for a months, potentially years. And for
the again, for the average consumer
who's already grasping, you know,
struggling with inflation, they need all
the relief they can get, and at the
pump, it's not going to be one of the
places they find it.
>> Yeah, so what we need to do here from
from this point forward is watch the
marketplace for clues about which way
we're going. So, the first thing you're
going to watch is WTI futures to see how
the curve reshapes in this next stage.
Yes, we're going to expect for the
entire curve to come down, but the
spreads and the amount of backwardation,
maybe even contango if we get that far.
Um that would be down the road, but
we're going to watch the WTI futures
curve for how it reacts to this next
stage for clues about which which which
which one are we going to get? Are we
going to supply normalization quickly,
or we're going to see more demand
destruction? Of course, the other thing
you're going to watch is interest rates,
just you know, the yield curve, the
shape of the yield curve, how that
behaves even as threats from central
bankers to hike rates. They're going to
continue They're not going to go away.
Just because oil prices are, you know,
coming low at the front end of the curve
is is is moving lower, uh the central
bankers are going to continue talking
about a higher and higher rates. And
like you said, Steve, you know, bond
yields in Europe after the ECB hiked
this past week were like, "Yeah, we
don't really see it." That reaction is
important because it tells you about
what the market's thinking about how
this eventually resolves. That's more of
a demand destruction type of signal. So,
if we see even more of that, that would
give us even further clues about what
this next stage is really developing
into. So, that's what we need to watch
because
we keep coming back to that historical
example.
Energy shocks are not inflationary.
Energy shocks are not inflationary. They
end up destroying demand, especially for
an economy that's weak to begin with,
which we got all sorts of data that
shows that, and which means they
they
they destroy enough demand, they don't
end in inflation, they end in
unemployment.